Feinstein International Center Records UA197
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Feinstein International Center Records
1998 -- 2015
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Feinstein International Center
Friedman School of Nutrition Science and Policy Student Council
UA197
250 Digital Object(s)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Transferred by the Feinstein International Center, 2008 -- 2019.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series: Annual reports and status updates; White papers; 2015 accessions; and 2020 accessions.
Biographical / Historical
The Alan Shawn Feinstein International Center was founded in 1996. The Center is part of the Friedman School of Nutrition Science and Policy at Tufts University, and it carries out field-based research in regions undergoing humanitarian crises.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains reports and publications produced by the Feinstein International Center and its researchers.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Centers and Institutes; Research and Research Administration; Foreign affairs
- Annual reports and status updates, 2004 -- 2012; UA197.003.000001; 12 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains annual reports and updates on projects related to the functioning of the Feinstein International Center.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged chronologically by accession number.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Annual Report, 2004 -- 2005; UA197.003.003.00001; Feinstein International Center
    The past year has been one of intense activity for the Center. Field research in Ethiopia, Darfur, Uganda, the Balkans, West Africa, and Afghanistan has resulted in the publication of a number of major reports which have been received with considerable interest by the humanitarian community. In addition, the Center has played a leading role in informing the peace and justice process in Northern Uganda. Center-led contributions to the British Medical Journal and other media have helped shape the policy debate around the international response to the tragic December 26th tsunami in the Indian Ocean.
    Feinstein International Center
  - Annual Report, 2005 -- 2006; UA197.003.003.00002; Feinstein International Center
    Strategic planning undertaken in 2004/5 has paid off. The Center has revised its research portfolio to focus on three critical themes of research: Lives and Livelihoods, Rights and Protection, and Politics and Policy. In July 2006, the Center staff moved into a new, larger space in an office building at the Tufts Medford campus, and we have opened a permanent second office in Addis Ababa. Our team of researchers, both in Medford and in Addis, has expanded over the year, and we are set to continue this expansion into 2006/7.
  - Deliverables, 2007; UA197.003.003.00003; Feinstein International Center
    In 2006 we focused primarily upon laying the groundwork and recruiting the faculty and staff to enable us to begin the intellectual and institutional change processes outlined above. We achieved most of our deliverables for 2006 and are extending several into 2007. However, the overall shape of our deliverables in the coming twelve months will differ substantially from those of the closing year. 2006 was about building the Center; 2007 is about putting it the change processes into action. The vast majority of our 2007 deliverables focus on research and education. Our change process is captured in seven key processes, as described in detail in our three year strategy. Under each of these processes we list here the milestones, outputs and impact we hope to realize in 2007.
  - Annual Report, 2006 -- 2007; UA197.003.003.00004; Feinstein International Center
    The year 2006/7 has been one of consolidation for the Feinstein International Center after major changes were implemented in the preceding year. We hired new faculty and staff, reinforced existing research, and enhanced our teaching agenda. We attracted new funders to the Center and are playing a larger role in the academic life of Tufts University. Our research in Sudan and Uganda has expanded. Recruitment to our faculty of Dr. Andrew Wilder, formally director of the Afghan Research and Evaluation Unit (AREU), paves the way for further expanding the geographical scope of the Center's research in South and Central Asia. Our partnerships with African universities and research groups continue, as do those with western aid agencies. We have started a new partnership with Transparency International on a research program into the prevalence and effects of corruption in the humanitarian aid business. Throughout the year, Center faculty have been sought out by UN agencies, NGOs, and government aid departments to facilitate, chair, and advise upon the changing nature of humanitarian threats and response. In our educational agenda we continue to offer our Masters of Arts in Humanitarian Assistance degree and contribute to teaching in the Friedman School of Nutrition Science and Policy as well as the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy. Our joint Humanitarian Studies initiative with Harvard and MIT has undergone a major upgrade and the number of Ph.D. students supported by Center faculty continues to increase. Looking forward to 2007/8, we envisage the start of major long-term research initiatives examining the effects of repeated crises on vulnerable communities, the opportunities being offered by the spread of cell phone technology in Africa, and the increasingly complex relationship between security, economics, and humanitarian need across the world.
  - Annual Report, 2008 -- 2009; UA197.003.003.00005; Feinstein International Center
    We are pleased to publish our annual report for 2008/09. This last year has proved an extraordinarily productive year for the Center. We have 34 active research projects across five major programs, carrying out research globally and in 12 countries. We produced 20 major Center reports, all freely available on our website, as well as numerous journal articles, two books, and five book chapters.
  - Annual Report, 2009 -- 2010; UA197.003.003.00006; Feinstein International Center
    The Center's scope of work has expanded in 2009-10 while staying focused on the subject matter of marginal communities and crisis. We now have active research ongoing in 14 countries around the world, with some thirty projects linking research to policy and practice change. In Sudan, Ethiopia, Uganda, and Afghanistan, our research has had a direct impact on government and independent aid programming, and globally our work with a number of leading NGOs and more generally in promoting notions of professionalism and evidence-driven aid are having impact.
  - Humanity and Dignity Through Knowledge: A Ten-Year Vision, 2005-06-24; UA197.003.003.00007; Feinstein International Center
    We have a vision of a future ten years from now in which famine, widespread violations of human rights, extreme suffering and crimes against humanity are held to be self-evidently unacceptable by states and their peoples. A vision in which nation states, and the international community, in all its manifestations, feel duty bound to act – and do act – to prevent and alleviate such abuses.
    Annual reports; Feinstein International Center
  - Humanity and Dignity Through Knowledge: A Three-Year Strategic Plan, 2005-07-19; UA197.003.003.00008; Feinstein International Center
    In this document we present the strategic plan of the Feinstein International Famine Center for the next three years. We explain how the Center will build on its current international status and expertise to enhance research, teaching and institutional change activities. We explain how it will respond to opportunities for growth, and how it will have greater impact in alleviating suffering and protecting the rights of marginalized and vulnerable people affected by conflict and crisis. Integral to the plan is the systematic use of processes to ensure that community-level needs and aspirations are understood and prioritized in the actions and policies of national and international bodies.
  - Research Update March 2006, 2006-04-26; UA197.003.003.00009; Feinstein International Center
    The Feinstein Center is presently running some 20 research and institutional change projects, under three broad themes of enquiry: Politics & Policy, Rights & Protection, and Lives & Livelihoods. This update briefly describes the present status of each of these pieces of work. Full reports on the projects will appear on the Center's web site as they are released and will be flagged in our regular six monthly Center Status Reports.
    Status report series; Feinstein International Center
  - Annual Report, 2010-2011, 2011-10-03; UA197.003.003.00010; Feinstein International Center
    The Centers scope of work has expanded in 201011 while staying focused on the subject matter of marginal communities and crisis. We now have active research ongoing in 14 countries around the world, with some 29 projects linking research to policy and practice change. In Sudan, Ethiopia, Uganda, and Afghanistan, our research has had a direct impact on government and independent aid programming, and globally our work with a number of leading NGOs and more generally in promoting notions of professionalism and evidence-driven aid are having impact.
  - Three Year Plan 2012-2014, 2011-06-07; UA197.003.003.00011; Feinstein International Center
    Since our founding in 1997, the Feinstein International Center has broadened into a multidisciplinary institution focused on providing the understanding, teaching, and evidence needed to drive positive change in policies and practices affecting crisis-affected communities. This plan describes our intended research, institutional change and education work over the period January 2012 December 2014. We will build on the success of the past and will focus our research efforts on seven critical areas of enquiry, outlined in Section Four. We will also continue to teach and mentor a diverse graduate student body, spanning three of Tufts' graduate schools, and prepare students for leadership in government and international bodies.
  - Annual Report 2011-2012, 2012-09-01; UA197.003.003.00012; Walker, Peter; This report covers the first year of our new three year strategy with its focus on seven critical areas of research. We now have active research ongoing in 16 countries around the world, with over 25 projects linking research to policy and practice change. In Sudan, Ethiopia, Uganda, and Afghanistan, our research has had a direct impact on government and independent aid programming, and globally our work with a number of leading NGOs and more generally in promoting notions of professionalism and evidence-driven aid are having impact.
- White papers, UA197.000267
  - Humanitarian Agenda 2015, 2004 -- 2010; UA197.001; 22 Digital Object(s)
    This series contains reports, studies and other materials from the Feinstein Center initiative "Humanitarian Agenda 2015."
    This series is arranged in the order documents were received.
    - Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Principles, Power, and Perceptions: Preliminary Report, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00001; Donini, Antonio; Minear, Larry; Azarbaijani-Moghaddam, Sippi; Hansen, Greg; Mowjee, Tasneem; Purushotma, Karina; Simillie, Ian; Stites, Elizabeth; Zeebroek, Xavier
      Report dated September, 2006. Since the beginning of 2006, an interdisciplinary team has been working on a wide-ranging evidence-based research project that identifies the key issues that are likely to impact on humanitarian action in the coming decade, along with the practical implications of these issues for agency programming. During the first phase of the project, which ended in August 2006, the team researched four interrelated issues: the universality of humanitarianism, the implications of terrorism and counter-terrorism for humanitarian action, the search for coherence between humanitarian and political agendas, and the security of humanitarian personnel and the beneficiaries of humanitarian action. Six case studies have been conducted and a preliminary report, Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Principles, Power and Perceptions, was published in September 2006.
      War on Terrorism, 2001-; Humanitarianism; Terrorism; Human rights; United Nations
    - Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Afghanistan Country Study, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00002; Donini, Antonio
      Paper dated June, 2006. This study is part of a research program undertaken by the Feinstein International Center at Tufts University on The Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Principles, Politics and Perceptions (HA 2015).1 The key findings of the research in Afghanistan are presented in the following pages under the four HA 2015 headings: the universality of the humanitarian enterprise; terror and counter-terror and its impact on humanitarian action; coherence of political and humanitarian endeavors; and issues related to security of communities and humanitarian personnel. This is preceded by a brief historical background and by an overview of Afghans perceptions of the aid effort. A final section presents key conclusions and (policy) recommendations. The four themes of the HA 2015 research come together in Afghanistan with clear-cut relevance. The externality of the aid enterprise and the baggage that comes with itvalues, lifestyle, attitude, and behavior of aid workerschallenge the purported universality of humanitarian action. The context of terrorism and counter-terrorism is at the heart of the international communitys involvement in Afghanistan: the initial objective of the US-led coalition was to smash Al Qaeda and the Taliban, not to engage in nation-building. The coherence agenda, exemplified both by the integration of humanitarian and human rights concerns within the United Nations Assistance Mission in Afghanistan (UNAMA) and by the pressures on NGOs to be part of the Coalitions combat team, colors the operating environment of the aid community. And the heavy toll inflicted by insurgents and criminal elements on the security of aid workers, both Afghan and international, cuts across the three other themes and deeply affects staff morale and ability to address critical humanitarian need.
      War on Terrorism, 2001-; Humanitarianism; Terrorism; Human rights; Qaida (Organization); Taliban; United Nations
    - Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Burundi and Liberia Country Studies, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00003; Zeebroek, Xavier
      Paper dated July, 2006. Burundi: Within the four topics addressed by the Humanitarian Agenda 2015 research, three seem pertinent in the case of Burundicoherence, security and, to a lesser extent, terrorism. Many comparisons can be made with Liberia, in terms of the length and cruelty of the war and the type of involvement of the international community. The integrated structure of the United Nations Mission in Liberia (UNMIL) strongly influenced the design of the UN mission in Burundi (ONUB), even if the role and functions of the UN Office for the Coordination of Humanitarian Affairs (OCHA) were eventually different. Parallels with Afghanistan and Sudan are also relevant regarding the integrated character of the missions and issues of security. Liberia: Within the four topics addressed by the Humanitarian Agenda 2015 report, only two seem pertinent in the case of Liberiacoherence and security. The United Nations Mission in Liberia (UNMIL) has become a model for the fully-integrated mission, and is likely to be followed by other UN missions in Africa, such as Burundi or Sudan. Parallels with Afghanistan can also be made regarding the absorption of OCHA within the integrated mission.
      War on Terrorism, 2001-; Humanitarianism; Terrorism; Human rights; Qaida (Organization); African Union
    - Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Colombia Country Study, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00004; Minear, Larry
      Paper dated July, 2006. This case study on Colombia was undertaken as part of a larger research initiative, The Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Principles, Power, and Perceptions (HA 2015), which seeks to analyze the major challenges facing the humanitarian enterprise during the coming decade. The experience of Columbia sheds light on all four themes of the HA 2015 research. First, with respect to universality, Colombia sees itself as part and parcel of the western world. There is broad resonance between Colombian religious and civil traditions and the global humanitarian ethos, laws, and institutions. Second, he focus group and individual interviews conducted for this study concentrated on terrorism, understood as violence or the threat of violence against ordinary civilians, against their life, their property, their well-being. [Terrorism] is a means to attain a political goal which allegedly could not be attained by ordinary, lawful means, within the context of the established constitutional order.5 A broadly held consensus emerged that what might be called small t terrorism was tearing apart the human, social, economic, and political fabric of Colombian society while introducing major complications into the functioning of international and domestic humanitarian and human rights organizations. At the same time, alleged connections to an overarching global war on terrorism (capital T terrorism) were found to be overdrawn. As for the third theme, coherence, the prevailing political framework promoted by the United States government in the form of Plan Colombia and embraced by the Colombian authorities in its own democratic security policy provides an uneasy fit for international assistance and protection activities and a point of tension between the US and other donors. Finally, with regard to security, there has been by most accounts an overall reduction in the incidence of specific forms of violence in late 2005 and early 2006 from the withering levels of the preceding five years. Yet a climate of fear still pervades many sectors of society and there were, at the time of the research visit, still numerous incidents taking place, including killings and harassment of leaders of civil society organizations.
      War on Terrorism, 2001-; Humanitarianism; Terrorism; Human rights; United Nations; Eje'rcito de Liberacio'n Nacional (Colombia); Fuerzas Armadas Revolucionarias de Colombia
    - Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Northern Uganda Country Study, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00005; Stites, Elizabeth
      Paper dated June, 2006. The HA2015 study examines the effects of four broad challenges on the humanitarian enterprise: universality, terrorism, coherence and security. Each of these has resonance in the context of northern Uganda. There are parallels between the Uganda case and other country studies in some aspects. The manifestation of the terrorism/counter-terrorism paradigm, for instance, has many parallels to Colombia. In other respects, such as the question of coherence, Uganda is unique in the countries examined to date.
      War on Terrorism, 2001-; Humanitarianism; Terrorism; Human rights; Uganda. People's Defence Forces; Lord's Resistance Army; National Resistance Army (Uganda); World Food Programme
    - 'Aid in a Pressure Cooker': Humanitarian Action in the Occupied Palestinian Territory, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00006; Fast, Larissa
      Paper dated november, 2006. The Humanitarian Agenda 2015 study (Donini et al. 2006) has examined the effects of four major challengesuniversality, terrorism, coherence, and securityto humanitarian action in context-specific situations. This study of the occupied Palestinian territory (oPt) is part of Phase II of HA2015 which includes a larger set of case studies. As with the other case studies, the present report offers insights into the way in which these four major variablesor petalsare interrelated and impact on humanitarian action.
      Israel-Arab War, 1967--Occupied territories; War on Terrorism, 2001-; Humanitarianism; Terrorism; Human rights; United Nations; Palestinian National Authority; Hizballah (Lebanon)
    - Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Sudan Country Study, 2006; UA197.001.DO.00007; Mowjee, Tasneem
      Paper dated July, 2006. As a result of the various conflicts, the political and economic situation in different parts of Sudan is very different. North Sudan is largely peaceful with a stable, well-established government rich from oil revenues, though unemployment is a major problem (people complain that it is very difficult to get jobs without the right government connections. As a result, young men are going to the Middle East or Europe in search of work). The conflict began because Darfur felt neglected by the authorities in Khartoum and excluded from the peace talks between North and South Sudan, but it is exacerbated by tribal conflict which began in the 1980s. With the signing of the CPA, South Sudan is heading towards sustainable peace, and people displaced by the war are returning gradually. Under the terms of the CPA, there is a unified3 UN mission to monitor its implementation in the South (though the Mission HQ is in Khartoum). However, since South Sudan had no government institutions for over 20 years, the fledgling Government of South Sudan (GoSS) is struggling to establish itself. There is almost no infrastructure either. Juba, the capital, has few whole buildings and had lost electricity at the time of the study due to the breakdown of generators supplying the town. Interviewees highlighted housing, sanitation, and jobs as their most pressing problems. The conflict in Darfur has raged for three years, resulting in 300,000 deaths and the displacement of over two million people.4 Most of the displaced have been living in IDP camps, though some have tried to find shelter in large towns or with relatives. Understandably, interviewees in the camps complained of a lack of employment, food, shelter, education, water, etc. The shortage of food was one of the greatest problems and this has undoubtedly been exacerbated since the World Food Programme had to halve rations from May 2006 due to a lack of contributions from donors. However, in some of the IDP camps, interviewees were also concerned about the lack of money and opportunities for young adults to get married or continue with a university education (most education services in the camps are up to primary or secondary school level only). The conflict began because Darfur felt neglected by the authorities in Khartoum and excluded from the peace talks between North and South Sudan, but it is exacerbated by tribal conflict which began in the 1980s.
      War on Terrorism, 2001-; Humanitarianism; Terrorism; Human rights; United Nations Mission in Sudan; African Mission in Sudan; African Union; United Nations; Qaida (Organization)
    - Taking Sides or Saving Lives: Existential Choices for the Humanitarian Enterprise in Iraq: Humanitarian Agenda 2015: Iraq Country Study, 2007; UA197.001.DO.00008; Hansen, Greg
      Paper dated June, 2007. Iraq places the frailties and fault-lines of the humanitarian enterprise in stark relief. Perhaps more than any other highly politicized context, Iraq has fuelled a defensiveness and sense of existential threat among many in the humanitarian profession. And yet, while Iraqis have paid long and dearly for the flaws in the international humanitarian apparatus, evidence from ground-level suggests that pronouncements of the demise of principled humanitarian action are premature. Iraq may provide the strongest affirmation yet of the endurance of the Dunantist ethos and of the principled practice of humanitarianism.